(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. Ooh, I'm like, "Phew, phew, calm down. Get back into my body now." (Laughter)
الهدوء. سأرجع إلى جسدي الآن.
Usually when I play out, the first thing that happens is
عادةً عندما ألعب، فأن أول شئ يحدث هو،
people scream out, "What's she doing?!"
يصرخ الناس، ماذا تفعل هي؟
I'll play at these rock shows, be on stage
أتعلمون، إني أعزف في عروض الروك هذه، وعندما أكون على المسرح،
standing completely still, and they're like,
وأقف بلا حراك .. كما ترون .. فقط أقوم بهذا
"What's she doing?! What's she doing?!"
يسألون ، مثل، ماذا تفعل هذه الفتاة ؟
And then I'll kind of be like -- (Vvvwow!) -- and then they're like, "Whoa!"
ثم بعد ذلك، نوع ما يستحسنوه مثل -- (فوووواو!)-- كما تعلمون، ثم ...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'm sure you're trying to figure out,
وإنه، أنا متأكدة من أنكم تحاولون معرفة،
"Well, how does this thing work?"
حسناً، كيف يعمل هذا الشئ؟
Well, what I'm doing is
حسناً، ما افعله هو -- أوه!--
controlling the pitch with my left hand.
أتحكم في النغمة بيدي اليسرى.
See, the closer I get to this antenna, the higher the note gets --
أنظروا، كلما أقتربت من هذا الهوائي، كلما تصبح النوتة أعلى.
(Portamento) --
(نغم)
and you can get it really low.
ويمكنك الحصول عليها منخفضة حقاً.
And with this hand I'm controlling the volume,
وبهذه اليد، أنا أتحكم في الصوت،
so the further away my right hand gets, the louder it gets.
لذا كلما أبتعدت يدي اليمنى، كلما أصبح الصوت عالياً.
(Tones)
(نغمات)
So basically, with both of your hands
إذاَ في الأساس، بكلا اليدين
you're controlling pitch and volume and kind of
تتحكم في النغمة والصوت، ونوع ما،
trying to create the illusion that you're doing separate notes,
محاولة صنع الوهم بأنك تفرّق النوتات
when really it's continuously going ...
حينماً، حقاً، تتواصل في اللعب...
(Flourish ... Beep)
(إزدهار...بيب)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Sometimes I startle myself: I'll forget that I have it on,
بعض الأحيان أباغت نفسي: وأنسى بأنها مازالت تعمل،
and I'll lean over to pick up something,
وعندما أميل لكي ألتقط شيئاً،
and then it goes like -- (Blip) -- "Oh!"
ثم تبدأ، مثل، أوه!
And it's like a funny sound effect that follows you around
وهي مثل تأثير الصوت المضحك الذي يتبعك
if you don't turn the thing off.
إن لم تقم بإغلاقه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Maybe we'll go into the next tune,
ربما يجب علينا أن نذهب إلى اللحن المقبل،
because I totally lost where this is going.
لأنني فقدت كلياً سياق الحديث.
We're going to do a song by David Mash called "Listen: the Words Are Gone,"
سنقوم بأداء أغنية لديفيد ماش تسمى" أسمع: لقد ضاعت الكلمات،"
and maybe I'll have words come back into me afterwards if I can relax.
وربما سأحصل على الكلمات مجدداً بعد ذلك.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So, I'm trying to think of some of the questions
إذاً، أنا أحاول التفكير في بعض الأسئلة
that are commonly asked; there are so many.
التي تُطرح عادة. إنها كثيرة للغاية.
And ... Well, I guess I could tell you
وحسناً، أخمّن أنه يمكنني إخباركم
a little of the history of the theremin.
القليل عن تاريخ الثيرمين.
It was invented around the 1920s, and the inventor, Léon Theremin
لقد تم إختراعه عام 1920 تقريباً، والمخترع، ليون ثيرمين
-- he also was a musician besides an inventor --
- وهو كذلك موسيقار إضافة لمخترع --
he came up with the idea for making the theremin,
لقد توصل لفكرة صنع الثيرمين
I think, when he was working on some shortwave radios.
أعتقد بينما كان يعمل على مذياع ذا موجة قصيرة
And there'd be that sound in the signal -- it's like (Screeching) --
وسيكون هناك ذلك الصوت في الإشارة -- إنه مثل -- (صراخ)
and he thought, "Oh, what if I could control that sound
وقد فكر، أوه، ماذا إن أستطعت التحكم بذلك الصوت
and turn it into an instrument, because there are pitches in it."
وتحويله إلى آلة، لأن به نغمات.
And so somehow through developing that,
ولذا بطريقة ما، عبر تطوير ذلك،
he eventually came to make the theremin the way it is now.
توصل في نهاية المطاف لصنع الثيرمين بالطريقة التي عليه الآن.
And a lot of times, even kids nowadays,
والكثير من الأوقات حتى الأطفال هذه الأيام،
they'll make reference to a theremin by going, "Whoo-hoo-hoo-hoo,"
يقومون بالإشارة للثيرمين خاصتي بأن يفعلوا "أوهه-هوو-هوو-هوو،
because in the '50s it was used in the sci-fi horror movies,
لأنه خلال الخمسينات كان يستخدم في أفلام الخيال العلمي المرعبة:
that sound that's like ... (Woo-hoo-hoo-hoo)
ذلك الصوت مثل...(هوو-ووو)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's kind of a funny, goofy sound to do.
إنه نوع ما، يفعلون الصوت المضحك المخيف.
And sometimes if I have too much coffee,
وبعض الأحيان إذا شربت الكثير من القهوة،
then my vibrato gets out of hand.
فأن الإهتزازات تخرج عن نطاق سيطرتي.
You're really sensitive to your body and its functions
فأنت حساس للغاية تجاه جسمك وعمله
when you're behind this thing.
عندما تكون خلف هذا الشئ.
You have to stay so still if you want to have the most control.
ينبغي عليك الإنتظار إن أردت السيطرة الكاملة.
It reminds me of the balancing act earlier on -- what Michael was doing --
إنه يذكرني بفعل التوازن باكراً، ما كان يفعله مايكل،
because you're fighting so hard to keep the balance
لأنك تقاتل بشدة للإحتفاظ بالتوازن
with what you're playing with and stay in tune, and at the same time
مع ما تلعبه، وتبقى على اللحن، وفي نفس الوقت
you don't want to focus so much on being in tune all the time;
فأنت لا تريد التركيز كثيراً على البقاء في تناغم طوال الوقت.
you want to be feeling the music.
تريد أن تشعر بالموسيقى.
And then also, you're trying to stay very, very, very still
ثم تحاول كذلك البقاء بحذر شديد للغاية،
because little movements with other parts of your body
لأن أقل حركة من بقية جسدك
will affect the pitch, or sometimes if you're holding a low note -- (Tone rising out of key) --
ستؤثر على النغمة، أو بعض الأحيان إن كنت تصدر نوتة منخفضة،
and breathing will make it ...
وتتنفس، كما تعلمون، ستخرج هكذا...(نغمة خارجة من المفتاح)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If I pass out on the next song ...
إذا واصلت إلى الأغنية التالية--
I think of it almost like
لكن من المؤكد، أنا افكر بها غالباً، مثل،
like a yoga instrument because it makes you so aware
مثل آلة اليوغا، لأنها تجعلك متيقظ للغاية
of every little crazy thing your body is doing,
لكل شئ صغير يفعله جسدك،
or just aware of what you don't want it to be doing
أو مجرد الوعي بما لا تريد أن تفعله
while you're playing; you don't want to have any sudden movements.
بينما تقوم باللعب: كما تعلمون، أخذ حركات مفاجئة.
And if I go to a club and play a gig, people are like,
وإذا ذهبت إلى النادي ولعبت صوت مزعج، يقوم الناس ب،
"Here, have some drinks on us!"
" هنا تعالي وأشربي مشروب على حسابنا!"
And it's like, "Well, I'm about to go on soon;
وإنه مثل، كنت على وشك الذهاب.
I don't want to be like -- (Teetering tones) -- you know?"
أنا لا أريد أن أكون مثل، (نغمات متأرجحة)
It really does reflect the mood that you're in also,
إنها لا تعكس حقاً المزاج الذي أنت فيه، كذلك
if you're ...
إن كنت، كما تعلمون، إن كنت --
it's similar to being a vocalist, except
إنه شبيه بأن تصبح مطرباً ، بإستثناء،
instead of it coming out of your throat,
بدلاً عن أن تخرج الأصوات من حلقك،
you're controlling it just in the air
فأنت تتحكم بها فقط عبر الهواء
and you don't really have a point of reference;
وليس لديك حقاً نقطة مرجعية.
you're always relying on your ears and adjusting constantly.
فأنت تعتمد دائماً على أذنيك وتقوم بالضبط بإستمرار.
You just have to always adjust to what's happening
ينبغي عليك الضبط دائماً مع ما يحدث
and realize you'll have bummer notes come here and there
وتدرك أنك ستحصل على نوتات غريبة تأتي من هنا وهناك
and listen to it, adjust it, and just move on,
وتستمع إليها، تضبطها، وتواصل فقط،
or else you'll get too tied up and go crazy. Like me.
أو أنك ستتقيد بشدة وتصاب بالغضب. مثلي.
I think we will play another tune now.
أرغب في عزف نغمة أخرى الآن.
I'm going to do "Lush Life." It's one of my favorite tunes to play.
سأقوم بعزف " حياة مورقة": إنها أحدى نغماتي المفضلة لألعبها.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)